[Music]
This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
Classical mechanics
is the basis for all of physics.
It's the basis of all of physics not
only because uh it describes the motion
of objects like particles and mechanical
systems and so forth but because the
basic framework the basic um structure
of all of physics is based on the
principles of classical mechanics. The
conservation of energy, the conservation
of momentum,
uh the principles by which all systems
evolve in nature is the same set of
rules essentially exactly the same set
of rules in a more abstract in a more
general setting than the rules which
govern how a simple particle moves for
example under the influence of gravity.
But in order to understand it, we have
to understand the principles in a fairly
general context.
Uh let's begin with the very very
simplest kinds of systems that we can
think of. Systems that are so simple
that in fact they're simpler than any
real uh systems in
nature. Laws of nature. Let's imagine
laws of nature which are of the most
primitive and simple
kind acting on the most primitive and
simple systems that we can imagine. I
want you to first of all suppose that
time which evolves continuously under
the my watch I see the second hand goes
around and around and around. It goes
around continuously. The time can evolve
and be any real
number t. I want you to imagine it only
occurs in beats. a strooscopic world in
which you only look at the world at
intervals of time which we could be a
thousandth of a second or it could be a
millionth of a second. Let's just take
it to be 1 second
intervals and ask how in the
stroboscopic world systems change with
time. Let's also imagine a very very
simple set of systems. Systems which are
so simple that they only have a handful
of
configurations. Configurations mean
everything we need to know about the
system to characterize it completely. So
the simplest system I can think of would
be a system that has only two
configurations. Heads or tails. A coin.
Lay a coin down on the table. I don't
have a coin. So we'll take uh this
coffee top here. I could put it down
heads or I could put it down tails. I
doubt if you can tell the difference
from where you're sitting, but I can
tell the difference. This is this is
heads. That's tails. All right. So, we
have a system then that's characterized
by two
states. Two states of
being. And we want to add to those two
states a law, a law of evolution in
going from one instant of time to the
next instant of time. From one beat of
the strooscopic light to the next one.
What kind of laws are allowable? What
kind of laws do the basic principles of
physics allow? And what kind of laws
don't they
allow? That's going to be our first kind
of question for tonight.
So our first
concept is the space of states. In this
case, just heads and tails. It's just
two points. Heads and tails. Well, two
points in an abstract space.
heads and
tails. It's called a phase space. It's
called a phase space of a system. The
space of possible states of a
system. And what do I mean by a state of
a system? I mean everything that you
need to know in order to predict what
happens
next. Everything you need to know in
order to be able to say with certainty
what the next state of the system will
be. That's called the phase space of the
system. In this case, just heads and
tails. What kind of laws can you
imagine? What kind of laws of nature can
you imagine for this extremely simple
world? It is the simplest. Well, I
suppose you could imagine a slightly
simpler world. You can imagine a world
with only one state, heads. Not much can
happen in that world. There's only one
law of physics. Heads goes to heads. And
heads goes to heads goes to heads. It's
extremely boring. Nothing ever happens
because there's only one state. So how
could anything happen? But with two
states, heads and tails, you can have a
richer variety of possible laws of
physics. One law, let's take the various
varieties of laws of physics. We could
have one law might just
say you stay the same. If the state of
the system is heads at one instant of
time, then the next instant of time it
will be heads. If it starts tails, it
will stay tails. That's a very boring
law. And let's graph that law by drawing
an arrow. If it starts heads, then it
stays heads. Let's just represent that
by drawing an arrow from head to head
and from tail to tail. The meaning of
this arrow, you start at the tail end of
the arrow and you follow it and you see
that it comes around to the same point.
That stands for the rule that says that
a heads stays ahead. And in this case, a
tail stays a tail. So there's a very
dull law of nature. This stays that way
for endless amounts of time. And this
stays that way for endless amounts of
time. Another possible law of nature
would
be slightly more interesting situation.
If you look at it at one instant of
time, the next instant it's the
opposite. Heads goes to tails goes to
heads goes to tails. These are
deterministic laws. Deterministic laws
mean that if you know what is happening
at one instant, you know forever
after. You know everything about the
system infinitely into the future.
Completely deterministic. Classical
mechanics has that nature to it that it
is completely deterministic.
It always reversible
and in fact it is in a certain sense
always reversible. But uh we're coming
to that. All right. So to draw the graph
representing heads goes to tails and
tails goes to heads. We draw an arrow
from heads to tails. And from tails to
heads. And we read that as saying that
if you start at heads, you go to tails.
If you start at tails, you go to heads.
What is the evolution of a system under
this law of nature? If you start with
heads, it's heads, tails, heads, tails,
heads, tails, heads, tails forever
after.
These are two consistent laws of uh of
physics in a world of only two states.
Okay. Whether we can think of more laws.
Yes, we can. But uh but for the moment,
these are two interesting ones. Now, how
can we generalize this? We can
generalize this first of all to systems
with more states. Two states is not very
many. We could have a die. A die as in
dice. Die has six states. 1 2 3 4 5 and
six and we could represent them as
points six
points. Now we have a large variety of
different laws of physics that we could
have. For example, we could simply have
we could label these 1 2 3 4 5 and six.
Which one is one and which one is six is
not very important but uh but there are
six of them. We could have a law of
physics which says one goes to two, two
goes to three, three goes to four, four
goes to five, five goes to six and six
goes back to one. This would be a
complicated motion when thought of in
terms of a die. You start with a one up
and then it goes to the two up, three up
and so forth. But it's a relatively
simple picture when drawn in this manner
here. You can imagine more complicated
laws of physics with six states. Well,
whether they're more complicated or not
is in the eye of the beholder. But uh uh
first of all, we could have a similar
law where instead of one going to two,
one could go to
three, three could go to
two, two could go to
five, one, two,
three, something like that. That's
really not very different than this.
Each one goes to a neighboring one.
Well, not to a neighboring one. Each one
goes to a next one and they cycle
around. And one characteristic of such
systems is they will just cycle around
forever and ever and ever. Okay. Now,
you can have more
complicated I don't know if they're more
complicated, different laws. For
example, you could have a law which goes
this way.
If you start at one, you go to two. If
you go to two, then you go to three. And
then you go back to one. If you happen
to start at three, no, this isn't three.
This is five, right? Five. Six. Six.
Six. Six. 1 2 3 four five. If you start
at three, you go to four. If you start
at four, you go to five. Back to three.
In this case, well, that's somewhat
similar to this. You have two
disconnected
cycles. Two. We can have more
complicated things. Here's another
one. In fact, I think it would take a
long time to draw all the
possibilities. One goes back to
one, two goes to three, three goes to
four, four goes back to two,
uh, five goes to six, and six goes back
to five, right? They're all acceptable
laws of physics. Wherever you happen to
be, you know exactly where to go next.
So it's
deterministic. It's deterministic into
the future. Meaning to say wherever you
start, you know where you will be
arbitrarily into the future. If you
start here and you go a 100,000 times,
you'll just wind up, I don't know, some
wherever, wherever. If you start here,
you stay there. So these are completely
deterministic into the future, but
they're also completely deterministic
into the past. Which means if you know
where you are, you know where you were
before. If you find yourself over here,
then you know in the previous cycle or
the previous instant you were over here
and so forth. So you can trace your
motion either into the future or into
the past with complete confidence about
where you'll be no matter how far you
go.
That's the character in principle. In
principle, if not in uh practice. In
practice, things get jumbled up and you
can't see them clearly enough and you uh
and you miss detail. But if you see the
infinitely small detail in a system and
get every single bit of physics
absolutely right for any classical
system, they are in this sense exactly
deterministic both into the past and
into the future.
Now, what kind of laws of physics do we
not
allow? The kind of laws of physics that
we don't allow, I can best illustrate, I
think, by drawing some uh some
possibilities and explaining to you why
they are not
allowed. Here's a law of
physics that is not allowed by the
principles of classical physics. Three
states, three states is perfectly all
right. Nothing wrong with that. But
let's draw some arrows. Two, three, two
goes to three and three goes back to
two. That would be perfectly all right
by itself. What about one? Well, I could
have one goes to one, but I don't want
one to go to one. I want one to go to
two. That's completely deterministic
into the future. If I start at one, I go
to two. I go to two, I go to three, I go
three, back to two, two, back to three.
I always know where to go in the next
step. I just follow the arrow wherever
it happens to be. But what does it fail?
It fails to be deterministic into the
past. Uh supposing I know that I'm at
two. Then where did I come from? I could
have come from one or I could have come
from
three. So I cannot work my way backward
with uniqueness. I can work my way
forward. I cannot work my way
backward. That's a This is a law of
physics which is
irreversible. It would not allow me to
run the laws of physics backward. It
would lead to an ambiguity every time I
were at two. Another law which is not
allowed by the principles of classical
mechanics or principles of classical
physics would be basically the same
thing but with the arrows turned in the
opposite direction.
Uh, all arrows
reversed here. I have a problem not
going into the past, but I have a
problem going into the
future. Let's see. Um, yeah, supposing
now I find myself at two and I want to
go into the future. I don't know whether
to go into the future by following this
arrow to one or this arrow to three.
There are two arrows leading out of two
over here. One of them goes to three.
one of them goes to one. Nothing tells
me which arrow to follow. So it's not
deterministic into the future. I I might
uh randomly decide to go from two to
three or randomly decide to go from two
to
one. These are
rules each one of which is deterministic
in one direction but not the other.
These are the sorts of things which are
forbidden by the principles of classical
mechanics. Why are they forbidden by the
principles? Yeah. What if you just
erased one of those lines? One of those.
Which one? Yeah. Just one of those two
lines on the blue there. Yeah. That
wouldn't come. I wouldn't know where to
go from
three. You get stuck at three. Yeah.
Yeah. No good.
Can you ever have say a dangling one
over here? No, you can't have a dangling
one. You got to know where to go next.
Now you could let's see we could try to
put something like that in. Yeah.
Okay. So that would say we go from one
to two, from two to three to three to
three to three. Now the problem would be
in going backward I think. Right. Don't
know where you come from. Three or two.
Yeah. Right. So one way or the other you
get stuck uh with these rules. All
right. How do we spot what's allowable
and what's not allowable? Well, it's
very simple.
At every
configuration, two, three, we should
have one in and one out. We should have
a unique one in, a unique arrow in, and
a unique arrow out. One arrow in to tell
us where we came from, and one arrow out
to tell us where we're
going. That's the character of classical
physics. Uniqueness into the future,
uniqueness into the past. When
represented in terms of this very simple
an analog world uh analog digital world
of a finite number of
states then the rules of physics as we
know them would say every configuration
has one in arrow and one out arrow. Now
with this rule, of
course, life is very boring because if
you only have a finite number of states,
all that can happen to you is you cycle
around endlessly among those number of
states, always in the same
order. You can have slightly more
interesting situations. There's no
reason why the number of states has to
be finite.
You could have a situation where there's
an infinite number of possible
states. A state corresponding to every
integer positive and
negative. Uh a particle on a position on
a line where the position could be any
integer value. And then a simple law of
physics would be you go from one to the
next. Wherever you are, you go to the
next one.
Each point has one in and one out. I
can't draw them endlessly. It'll take
forever. But each mark, one in and one
out. This, of course, would also be a
rather boring law of nature. You just
hop from one to the next to the next and
the next to the next forever and ever
and ever. But at least you wouldn't be
cycling around
endlessly. Again, we could
have add some more states on to this. We
could add this on.
If we start on the line, we simply move
off and keep going forever and ever and
ever. But if we start over here, we
cycle
around. So we could have mixtures of
both kinds of things. Some states we
cycle around in, other states we move
off to infinity.
Now notice that some of these laws of
nature the phase space breaks up into
different pieces which are connected
among themselves but not connected to
each
other. For example, even with just two
states, we had two possibilities, one
like
this and one like
this. In this case where it breaks up
into more than one uh more than one
piece, we have something called a
conservation law. A conservation law is
simply a
memory of where we
started. A conservation law means that
something is kept intact for all time.
Some piece of knowledge is kept intact
for all time and doesn't change. In this
case, we could label this. We could
label a configuration over here with a
plus one and a configuration over here
with a minus one. And then we could call
we could invent a
variable + one over here and minus one
over here. It never changes. If it's
plus one, it stays plus one. If it's
minus one, it stays minus1. That's a
conservation law. Something which
doesn't change with time. On the other
hand, if we hop from plus one to minus1
to plus one to minus1, we don't have a
conservation law.
Conservation laws are always associated
with these kind of closed families of
different trajectories in the phase
space which don't mix with each other
which remember
um something about the system which
might otherwise get mixed up if
everything got all mixed together. So
there's all kinds
of possibilities that are inherent in
these deterministic laws. But always the
condition is one inline and one outline
for every
point. That can also be called
information conservation.
It's information
conservation in exactly the sense uh
that uh that you never lose memory of
where you started either into the past
or into the future. If you know where
you are at any instant, you know where
you came from and you know where you'll
be. Information about where you are is
conserved. Never changes into the past
and the future. Whereas if you have one
of these bad laws,
laws which are forbidden by the rules of
classical mechanics, then you do lose
information. For example, if you find
yourself over here, you don't know
whether you came from here or from well,
no, that's not quite right. If you find
yourself over here, you don't know
whether you came from here or over here.
So, you lose information.
uh information conservation is perhaps
the most fundamental law of basic
classical physics that you don't lose
information about. Now why that why is
that so?
Um it's not written into the laws of
physics why they are what they are.
Maybe someday we'll understand hyper
laws of physics or meta laws of physics
or deeper laws of physics which will
tell us why the laws of physics are what
they are. At the moment, it's more or
less an experimental fact that all the
known laws of physics fit into this
class of information conserving laws,
even those which are quantum
mechanical. But for our subject this
quarter, we're only interested in
classical physics. All right. So, that's
the basic setup. If we were interested
only in this stroboscopic world of
discrete time intervals,
um the real world of course is more
continuous than
that.
Supposing. Okay. So let's make the law
something like this.
If the last two states were heads
heads, then it stays
heads. If the last two states were heads
tails, then it goes to
heads. If the last two were heads,
tails, heads, then it goes to tails. And
if the last two were tails, tails, then
it goes to tails. I think that's a a
possible
uh a possible
law. Then you would say I can't tell
from the fact that its heads where it
goes next. And indeed I can't. But that
would just be another way of saying that
a specification of a heads by itself is
not what you would call a state. What
you would call a state would be the
specification of the previous last two
entries because you need two entries to
tell you what happens
next. Now that raises the question that
that that's very very important in
classical mechanics. How much and what
exactly do you need to know to say what
happens
next? If the phase space is the space of
things space of
possibilities but always in such a way
that they tell you exactly what happens
next. What is it that you do have to
know next? So that brings us to
continuous
physics. Let's take the motion of a
particle. Let's take the motion of a
particle. Is it enough to know where a
particle is to say what happens next?
Let's
hypothesize that the generalization to
continuous time is that we need to know
the exact location of a particle along a
line. We've run out of ink, I'm
afraid. Ah, there it
is. All right. So, let's imagine the
motion of a particle along a
line. Then you might think that the
analog of a state is just the location
of a particle. Where is it? But is it
enough to know where a particle is in
order to uh to say what happens next?
No. What else do you need to know?
Its
velocity. In order to know where a
particle will be next, you need to know
not only where it is, but how fast it's
moving. You need to know its velocity.
So that means the state in the same
sense that I used it that which you need
to know in order to know what happens
next does not just consist of the
location of a
particle but you can say it two ways.
You need to know not just the location
of the particle but you need to know
also the previous location or better yet
what cause or what what is equivalent to
knowing the previous location the
velocity right the velocity that tells
you that the phase
space the space of states the space of
configurations is two-dimensional noted
one-dimensional it's not just a
line it's a line that represents the
position of the particle and a second
line which represents its velocity
either to the left or to the right.
Positive velocity means moving to the
right. Negative velocity means moving to
the left. Supposing you're over
here, where do you move next?
You stay the same place. Why? You're at
the origin and you have no
velocity. What if you're over? So we
could just we could draw a little loop
here to say that you come back to the
same place. What if you're over here?
You stay the same place because you're
moving with zero velocity. Vertical axis
is velocity. So you come back to the
same
place. What if you're over
here? Where are you one second later?
Let's chop time up into 1 second
intervals. Where are you next?
Somewhere to the right. Huh?
What if you're over
here? Now, what if you're over here?
Move twice as far or roughly twice as
far to the
right. What if you're down here?
You move to the left.
So we could fill up this space here with
little tiny arrows to show where you
move next. But notice to know where you
move next, you have to know not only
where you are in the sense of what x is,
but you also have to know the vertical
component, namely what the velocity is.
So that means the
analog the analog of a point in the
phase space is a point in a space not
only of positions but also velocities.
Yeah.
So there's a conceptual issue here that
I don't understand that is you would
think that if you were able to
discretize time finally enough yes the
two should be the same and yet a
velocity that came in which isn't
readily apparent where that would take
place if you had these infinitely small
discrete time. It means um
representation of that. No it means
exactly what the gentleman asked me
before. What if you had a law of nature
which tells you in order to know where
to move next you had to know your
previous two entries right now one way
of saying it is all right in that case I
need to know the previous two entries
and it just doesn't fall into this class
of things or you could say that the
space of configurations doesn't just
consist of a heads or a tails but it
consists of a pair of entries a pair. So
we can model that with time the same.
That's right. We we model that. That's
right. We need two axes instead. That's
right. We need an axis for the present
configuration and the past one. Yeah,
that's exactly right.
Also in classical physics, do you ever
really know your state? Well, of course
not because in classical physics, the
position of a particle and so forth is a
real number.
A real number is uh something that you
can never determine
exactly. Uh and so there's always
imprecision and that imprecision always
represents a degree of uncertainty in
where you will be next. Now it gets
worse and worse in general. It's likely
to get worse and worse as you try to
take larger and larger time intervals. a
given degree of imprecision in what you
actually know can get magnified and get
uh magnified into worse and worse
imprecision as time goes on. So uh in
practice in
practice classical systems don't really
have the property that you can predict
endlessly where they're going to be and
exactly what they're going to do. But
you can always say given a time interval
I want to be able to predict exactly for
the next 30 seconds where every molecule
in this room will be. Let's forget
quantum mechanics now. Uh I want to be
able to pres predict exactly where every
molecule will be. Then there's a certain
degree of precision in the present
information at exactly one instant of
time which will permit me to be able to
extrapolate for 30 seconds.
Okay, it will not permit me to
extrapolate for 40 seconds. If I try to
extrapolate for 40 seconds, I will find
the errors get magnified out of control.
If I want to predict correctly for 40
seconds, I will have to do even better
in my initial conditions, in my
knowledge of exactly what the the state
of the system is. So in practice, this
idea of determinism is defective. It's
defective because in order to determine
for a given length of time you have to
have precision which is so good that
it's way way beyond anything anybody can
do. But in principle given any length of
time in classical physics there exists a
degree of precision which allows you to
extrapolate for that length of time.
Does that answer the question? Yeah. Uh
so some systems are very
predictable. Some systems are less
predictable and get out of control very
quickly. They're called chaotic systems
but uh the principles are the same that
it's just a degree of precision which
you need to know in the beginning in
order to extrapolate for a given length
of time.
You would say the system is still
deterministic. It's just not
predictable.
Well, you could uh I'm not sure what the
difference between predictable and
detchably so I can't say that. I think
they're conceptually quite different.
And you could say that these are the
equations that match reality and they
are deterministic. This is no way out
except that they don't give you an
algorithm to predict because prediction
requires a measurement.
Okay. Okay.
Yeah. Right.
What's that? Probability of
predictability.
Yeah. Right. The equations are
deterministic if you know the initial
conditions are deterministic are
predictable infinitely predictable if
you know the initial conditions with
infinite uh precision. You never do and
therefore they're never completely
predictable.
Um,
now
the fact that you need to know both the
position and the velocity in classical
physics in order to predict what happens
next reflects itself in the structure of
the equations of mechanics.
Specifically, it tells you that the
equations of motion, Newton's equations
in this case, are what are called second
order equations instead of first order
equations. Let me illustrate it by
starting with a first order equation. A
first order equation, what a first order
equation means is that it only has
quantities of first derivatives with
respect to time. In other words, only
contains velocities. Second order means
it contains not only first derivatives
but second derivatives means it contains
accelerations. The equations of motion
acceleration is the second derivative of
the
motion.
Um we could
write we know what the real equations of
motion of Newton are. F= ma it contains
acceleration. Let's write a phony
equation. Let's write F equals mass time
velocity.
Force is F. Velocity is velocity. And
let's suppose that force just depends on
where you are. We have a particle that
moves along a line. It's subject to
forces which vary along the
line. Right? Force may be big here,
small there, and so forth. So the force
depends on
position. And let's imagine this fake
equation of motion that it's equal to
mass times velocity. And what is
velocity? Velocity is the time
derivative of the position dx by
dt. And I will use continuously
throughout this course the notation that
time
derivative is just indicated by a dot.
Dot means time
derivative. All right. What does this
tell me? What do I need to know in order
to predict what happens next? I say for
this equation, we only need to know the
position of a particle. If we know the
position of a particle, I can tell you
what the velocity is just from the
equation. If I know that the position is
a particular position, then I know the
force on it. And from the equation, that
tells me what the velocity is. Does it
tell me the acceleration? How about the
acceleration? Let's see if I can compute
the acceleration.
To compute the acceleration from this
equation, we just differentiate it once
more. We write that df by
dt is equal to mass. Mass is just a
constant times the second derivative of
of the position or just the
acceleration. So we have over here
acceleration.
What about the fdt? The time derivative
of the
force. The force varies with time
because the position varies with
time. Right? So df by dt is just a
reflection of the fact that the position
of the particle varies with time. And we
can write the f by dt using the standard
rules of calculus as just you the the
change in f with respect to
position times the change in position
with respect to time.
In other words, the
velocity. All right, we've already
figured out what the velocity is.
Knowing the force, knowing the position,
so we know the velocity, and we can read
off from this equation what the
acceleration
is. We can figure out all of the
derivatives of the motion. If we know
where the particle is by multiply
differentiating this equation. So what
it tells us to make a short story out of
it is it tells us that if we know where
the position of the particle at any
instant of time then we know where it's
going to be in the next instant the next
two instance the next three instance it
completely predicts the motion. But this
is not the character of Newton's
equations. Newton's equations say F is
equal to mass time acceleration not mass
time
velocity. So let's look at this
equation.
F equals mass time acceleration. Can I
predict from this what the velocity is?
No. There's just no equation for the
velocity. Right? If I know what the
position is, I know what the force
is that tells me what the acceleration
is. But there's nothing in these
equations which tell me what the
velocity is. That means I have to add in
the velocity as a piece of information
to begin with. I have no choice. I have
to tell you in order to predict I have
to tell you the position as well as the
velocity. Then if I know the position
and the
velocity I can then predict the
acceleration next to a third derivative
the fourth derivative and all of them.
So that tells me that in order to know
where I am and where I'm going to be I
have to know the position and the
velocity. the phase space is a
two-dimensional space. So we see then
that
um that classical mechanics does have
this character of a configur or a phase
space of different
configurations with a set of little
arrows which tell you where to go next.
But the phase space
itself has a position component to it
and a velocity component to it. Right?
We will go on and study the classical
equations of motion and study them in a
variety of different
formulations. But always
the connecting link will always be
conservation of information. The idea
that the laws of physics are completely
deterministic and described by equations
which tell you where you will be next.
That's the character of classical
physics. Okay. That's a result of this
bifurcated system. Bifrocated
heads and tails up. Instead of being one
system, you need two pieces of
information.
It's one system, but you need two pieces
of information instead of one. Yeah. If
it weren't bifrocated, then you would
I'm not sure what you mean by
bifurcated.
Two
pieces of tails up
there. The very top up here. Here you
only need No, no. Here you need one
piece of information to say where you'll
be next. If you're here, you stay here.
If you're there, you stay there. But the
system is heads and tails. The rules
complicated, but the states are only
one. It's just all there is is heads and
tails. That's all there is. And if you
know where you are, you know where
you'll be next.
You know, when there were six states,
then then he had six rules. You can have
more rules, but basically No, no, no,
wait, no, no, no, no. There's one rule
coordinate for the for the what the dice
was
initial. So you only had one piece of
information. No, this this is one rule.
Heads goes to heads, tails goes to
tails. That's a single
rule. And if you know that you're at
heads, then you know you'll be next at
heads. If you know you're at tails, you
know that's so you only need the piece
of information heads or tails. That does
it. That tells you
everything. Now we I suggested a
different uh
well.
Yeah. You don't need to know where you
were before. You only need to know where
you are now to know where you'll be
next.
So both of these
laws require only knowledge of where you
are at one instant to tell you where
you'll be next. You simply follow the if
you start someplace, you follow the
arrow until you come back or you follow
the arrow till you get to the next place
and that tells you where you'll be
next. You don't need any more
information than
that. The only question is what one of
these points corresponds to. Does one of
these cut points correspond to how much
information does it correspond to a
point in the
space? Is it enough to know heads or
tails to know what you'll do next? Or
might you need to know the two previous
things? That's a different that's a
different
setup. Um, okay. If you have a single
particle
space then that has six phase space
coordinates.
Let's let's wait. Let's stay with the
heads and tails for a minute. Let's
suppose that in order to say what
happens next, you need to know the
previous two
configurations. Let's do let's work out
that example and let's write it in this
form. All right, let's make up a law. I
think I had one down before. Heads.
Heads goes to
heads. Heads.
Tails goes to what?
Tails. Tails.
Heads goes to heads. And tails. Tails
goes to
tails. Okay.
Is there something wrong with that?
We got to switch one.
It only depends on the last state.
Oh, this only depends on heads. Go.
You're right. You're right. You're
right. You're right. Sorry. Sorry.
Sorry. Sorry. Heads. Yeah. We want this
one to go to tails.
Uh.
Second one goes to heads. Good. Yeah.
Oh, no.
That won't work.
What? What? What? What? What? Say it
again. Then the first then what happened
two times ago matters, but not the last
time. That's also true. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. See, it see it looks a little hard
to work an example, doesn't it? Um,
let's see. Switch the second one and
that'll do it. H. Switch the second one.
Switch the second one. This one. Make a
tails. Make a tails. Okay.
I think that's perfectly all right.
You lose information. Why? Well, okay.
Here's a here's a setup. Here's a setup.
If you know the previous two, then you
know what happens
next. In fact, uh let's let's now see if
we can make a table out of this. Not a
table, but a set of points. A set of
points. Then there are four
possibilities. is heads heads heads
tails tails heads and tails
tails. Okay, let's see.
Here's heads
heads heads
tails tails heads and tails
tails. Now supposing you
go from heads
heads to
heads. So this is heads
heads heads. That means you go from
heads heads to heads heads
right? You go from heads heads to heads
heads. Now supposing you go from let's
see what happens if you start with heads
tails. Where do you go to? Tails tails.
So you go from heads tails to tails
tails.
Okay.
Okay. What happens if you go from tails
tails?
Oh, we're going to run into trouble,
aren't we? Tails tails goes to tails.
So tails tails goes to tails tails. Bad.
Not allowable by the laws of
physics. Do
and now tails heads goes where?
Tails tails goes to tails tails.
Wait,
tails heads.
Tails heads goes to goes to heads
tails. So that goes here.
Well, it seems to me we got we should be
able to make a consistent law.
What?
This one. This one.
Oh, tails tails goes to uh tails tails
goes to heads. Yeah. Okay. So then tails
tails goes to
heads. And that means that tails tails
heads. So that means tails tails goes to
to tails heads.
Ah. Oh. Okay. Good. Good. Now we have a
workable law. Now we have a workable
law. The only thing we had to do was to
say that what we originally called a
configuration, namely a single heads or
tails, was not a complete specification
of information. A complete specification
of information
involved two pieces of information. And
once we recognized that we were able to
uh to
um to write this down as a law of
physics which is deterministic and
reversible. Okay. So you don't know offh
hand. You don't know to begin with what
pieces of information you need to know
in order to know what to do
next. But that's what a step that's what
the configuration space or that's what
the phase space is. It's the collection
of all the things you need to know to
know what happens next. Now, of course,
you could go beyond this. You could say,
I need to know the first three things in
order to know what happens next. You can
do that. You'll simply need more states
to make a deterministic
system.
Um, what would it mean in classical
mechanics to need more information than
the uh positions and
velocities? Suppose you needed the
positions, velocities and
accelerations. That would mean third
order differential equations. But what
would it say about the phase
space? It would mean you would need
positions, velocities and accelerations
uh to represent the phase
space. Okay, as it happens that is not
the case for classical mechanics. That's
an experimental fact.
Uh but it wouldn't stop us if we did if
we did need the accelerations. We would
just write third order equations and we
would make our phase space
three-dimensional.
[Music]
The preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.